I'm
calling to order the regular meeting of the Inland Wetlands and Watercourses Commission for the town of Andover,
Monday, 03/01/2021
at 7PM.
It is of course a Zoom virtual meeting which will be recorded in audio and glorious video taking up gigabytes of server space someplace in the
cloud.
For a roll call, I see
Commissioner Halsey,
Commissioner Larson,
and alternate
Monroe
present
and
alternate Monroe will be seated
for
Commissioner Smith.
Additions and changes
in order to the agenda
item number three, there are
several changes that need to be made here.
First of all, the addition of an item 8A
new business,
a permit application
dated
twenty twenty one-three
for the
proposed work around the Doris Chamberlain Nature Pawn.
Since we are adding an Item eight, we will subsequently
renumber
all items following.
We can delete
the item presently 10A
Doris Chamberlain Nature Pond brush clearing
since that will be covered under the new application.
We
can add
an item 11d
resignation
of chair
and
an item I'm sorry should have given you first 11b
as in boy
a revision of regulations
and schedule hearing.
Mindy we got that?
Okay good.
Are there any other
changes or modifications
to the agenda order that any commissioners wish to propose?
>> If we're adding the resignation of the chair, would it be the appropriate time to fill that slot?
>> We're
adding that as item,
Pardon, we'll discuss it under 10D.
I'm just saying other business. You're saying except resignation.
I'm sorry, should be eleven.
I
>> only heard resignation
I'm suggesting that we also address filling that slot as well. So,
that would be part of the discussion.
Thank you.
>> Okay,
I'd like to have a motion to revise
and modify
the minutes as noted.
So moved.
And a second. I'll second.
Okay, we've got a motion and a second to revise the agenda as previously described
on
well.
Have to again do this by roll call and scrolling across the screen
acting Commissioner Monroe
yes
>> Commissioner Larson aye
Commissioner Halsey
and Vice Chair Elliott also votes aye motion carries four zero zero.
Next item on the agenda
approval of the 01/26/2020
special meeting
which was posted on the web
and which I'm looking for on my desktop now.
Do I have a motion to approve those minutes?
I'd like to move to approve minutes as presented.
Okay,
have a second.
I'll second it.
>> Okay, motion
is second.
Any discussion?
Okay, seeing none again roll call.
William Monroe.
Yes.
Jud Larson.
>> I will abstain as I was not at the meeting.
Okay.
Jim Halsey.
Aye.
>> By Sherri Elliott also votes aye so the motion carries
to 3,301.
Next would be the minutes of the regular meeting
of 02/01/2021.
Again, I'd like a motion to approve those minutes.
>> I'll make the motion to approve the February 1 meeting minutes.
>> Okay,
and a second.
Second it okay
so motion by Larson second by Monroe to
approve the minutes
any discussion
Okay, just a couple of minor comments.
Well, sure.
>> On page three,
at the
top paragraph,
bottom line there talks about a B100A
compliance
plan that should
show a code compliant area. The word show is missing.
On page four,
the top paragraph,
the second line says application to application to construct so we should eliminate two application.
Correct.
>> And on page five,
the top paragraph, second line,
Townsend
Road
instead of Towson Road,
T 0 W N S E N D.
And that was all I had.
>> Any other
noted
corrections?
Okay, so we'll take that motion to be to approve the minutes as corrected.
And I'll ask for roll call vote.
Mr. Monroe.
Hi,
Mr. Larson. Aye.
Mr. Halisey.
Aye.
And Vice Chair Elliot also votes aye so the motion carries 400.
Next item on the agenda number
five public comment. Do any members of the public present have any comments
on the
business before the or business on the agenda
for tonight's meeting?
Okay, seeing none, I will move on to agenda item number six,
legal guidance updates.
We
had some correspondence
between
Agent Wagner
and
now almost ex chair
Raleigh
regarding some questions of
policy and procedure
regulations
with Attorney Brantz
and
I was copied on that and I'm going to give you just a little brief summary for now. We can discuss it some points further
under the topic of new business or other business, excuse me, now number 11.
The first question subsequently had to do with when we should hold hearings. You may recall we had a discussion of that
with regard to the 26 Old
Farms Road application will be on the agenda
momentarily.
The
close reading
of the
regulation in question
suggested that we need not hold a hearing
however, it was foolish of me to have interpreted
a regulation based simply on logic and close reading.
Attorney
Brantz's
opinion based on case law and
experience
with
hearings in both wetlands and zoning context
is that when in doubt, hold a hearing
or the default should be a hearing for any activity that we deem significant.
Again, we can talk about that further when we look at the
item I proposed for the agenda regarding the
Commission regulations.
Procedurally, however, it will mean that we should determine at the first receipt of an application whether or
not
it is a significant activity
per regulations
and
therefore whether or not we should have a hearing.
The second question had to do with the timeline
for the application for a permit modification.
Now, the short answer is yes, we should wait at least fourteen days
even though it's a modification.
It is a permit application
first and foremost.
The third
opinion,
again pertinent to the
application
for Old Farms Road had to do with the Army Corps'
wetland impacts regulations and permit process.
It's complicated
but the bottom line is that it's no concern of ours. We don't need to worry about it. It's not germane
to our permitting process.
It's an entirely independent matter and while there may be some coordination between
requirements,
it's up to us to decide if this
application
is
qualified
for approval
based on our regulations
and state statutes.
Okay,
again
if there are questions or discussion about this, I'd prefer to hold off until we get to the other business portion of the meeting. Just want to give you that summary because some of it is pertinent
to
an application that's on the agenda for tonight.
Okay, well that sinks on. We'll
move on then to the
aforementioned application
IWWC
twenty-thirty
six
for
application to construct wetland crossing
at
well with the present frontage 26 Old
Farms Road.
Since our last meeting,
we have received
additional
correspondence
in response
to
the
questions
that were raised, particularly
by Mr. Gruner,
who I see is now on the call.
The
document
labeled '26 Old Farms letter twenty million two hundred ten thousand two hundred twenty six REMA
was
distributed in an email
from
agent Wagner
and I believe that members of the Commission should have had access to it however
I found that when I clicked on the link for that letter
on the website
just about half an hour ago or so,
I found that the link was incorrect.
It went to a previous letter
labeled
1.22.
Okay,
so I'm hoping
that through the miracles of technical assistance and
desktop
sharing
the correct
version
of that letter
can be brought up.
There we go
And I believe that
George Logan is on the call.
Is that correct?
Maybe you could unmute. That is correct. I'm here.
>> Okay.
And rather than having me summarize
this response,
would ask that you
do us a favor.
>> I will certainly do that. So again, George Logan, Re Mycological Services. I'm out of Manchester. Right now I'm sitting in my home in Vernon.
So the report basically addresses
some of the comments that I heard or saw in the minutes of,
I think it was the minutes that you just approved.
Right.
>> And gave some thought to it. I went out to the field.
I think it was in February
12.
We had some discussions with Mr. Bushnell, who's also here in attendance.
I walked the site with
Mr. Korea,
one of the applicants.
The question that I had is,
having seen
the crossing before,
and that was addressed in my previous letter that you said was 1.22.
I want to take a second look and maybe focus a little more on
sort of the biology,
whatever biology one could see in the winter,
which is surprisingly more than you think.
I also talked with Mr. Bushnell and Carl Simov, who
is I think the hydraulic engineer that's also
been involved in this project,
wanted to define the sizes of the watersheds for the
Western Stream versus the Eastern Stream. As you know, those two streams
have a confluence just
below the crossing. And then, of course, there's another confluence with another watercourse and eventually gets down to the Hop River.
So what I did is I found out that the
Western Water shed was
twice as large almost as the Eastern one. So the Eastern one is a much smaller watershed.
The Western one is a larger watershed,
which makes sense
because
when I first looked at the stream
after the end of a significant rainstorm
back in January,
that was the only one that was flowing at the time
pretty well. You might have remembered some of the pictures that you saw in that report,
Whereas the Eastern Stream wasn't
flowing at all at that time. It hadn't responded to the storm. There's a couple of reasons for that. Not
only the small watershed, but there's also
a midstream
upper wetland that probably has some capacity in storing some
drainage before it's released downstream.
I wanted to see the streams for a couple of reasons. First, I wanted to
make
a differential assessment
if there was one of these two stream corridors.
And at that time, as you remember,
there had been
the term riparian corridor or riparian habitat had been put forth.
And so that's, as you saw from my report,
went into
talking about what that is and basically admitted that technically
any
corridor that is associated with a stream, whether the stream is intermittent or perennial,
is a riparian corridor. There's no doubt to that. But amid the differentiation that
in
the real world, so we speak, there is a gamut of functionality
between
intermittent streams with a small watershed versus ones with a bigger watershed versus
what we would call semi perennial streams.
Usually those are the ones for a variety of reasons might have
more water flowing for a longer period of time before they
dry out in the summer. And of course, perennial streams.
So there are services, ecological services that
are much more pronounced
in perennial streams and then lesser and lesser as you go into intermittent streams. Of course, every stream has
to be looked at as site specifically.
So I did that and I walked up the smaller stream, which by the way, immediately
from that
little Panhandle that comes off the road,
which is the right of way, I guess, for a potential
driveway, you
can see that the Western Stream
climbs up a little bit up in the topography, but for the most part, it's a wider corridor.
It's it's flatter or more gentle slopes as good bit of water should,
and it's associated with more wetlands that are that fringe the watercourse on both sides as you go up the corridor. A lot of this wetlands are actually the backyards
of a lot of residences.
Now I would have wished to go look in that stream too, but
I've had experiences where people don't want me walking in their backyard. So I said,
better not do that. Let's do a little more of a look see from afar and sort of a desktop evaluation.
And then I walked the smaller stream and I think I trespassed a little bit, but only for maybe 100 feet or so before I went back into the site.
What I discovered was
there was some flowage at that time in Eastern Stream, not a lot. As you recall, that stream
has a pitch to it. It has a higher grade, goes up
moderately steeply,
is in an incised ravine.
So I walked all the way to that bathroom that I mentioned.
What I discovered along the way as I turned rocks and did a cover searching
was that the only life that I saw,
and again, I compare what I saw on that day with what I saw
just a few days after another stream, which is also intermittent
in the town of North Haven and Hampden.
So I have a comparison in my mind.
The Hamden Stream
had a slightly bigger watershed, obviously.
It was loaded with macrobenthes,
stoneflies and
caddisflies and
other Macrobenthes.
But this one only had
case caddisflies.
And this is something that I have seen over the years
in these streams that will
flow for, especially if there's a wetland upstream, they will flow for a period of time,
but they dry out pretty fast or they're intermittent in the sense that they're temporarily flooded during a storm.
Right after a storm,
the watershed continues to
put some base flow out
and then it dries out and then it waits for the next storm. That's exactly what these
case caddisflies will do,
is they have the ability to
weather the
differential hydrology, if you will, because they can basically shut down and keep moisture in and then wait for the next
moisture event. And then they
will continue on their business and foraging
the substrate.
So that's the only thing I saw. Did identify
potentially
the family of
those species.
Incidentally,
particular family is
indicator of very good water quality.
Yeah, better Gossa somatidae.
I didn't take it a genus or
species. I'm sure that your
chair at that time would have appreciated that, but I didn't have the time.
So having had
that firsthand experience looking at sort of what one stream, how it differs from the other.
And then in my background, having some of the things that Mr. Bruner, who's here,
who I've known for a very long time.
Hi, Hank, how are doing?
Some of the comments that he had, especially regarding
the ecological integrity and connectivity of
streams as the stream corridors.
Focused a little more on the wood turtle, which we know is
in very good abundance on the Hop River still, thankfully.
Put all that to mind. Then we had some discussions which really
don't pertain as you
talked earlier so much to this commission. The discussion was with the Army Corps of Engineers with a couple of staff people up there, specifically
Corey Rose was one of them and Paula Kohlberg was the other one,
to kind of get my head straight as to
what the core thinks about
even intermittent stream corridors.
So we had a discussion which kind of informed me a little bit going forward,
something else that we will have to do pass this commission.
The decision
was made, I'll let Mr. Bushnell explain that a little more,
that
the more significant corridor
for a number of reasons,
and even for wood turtle because
if it reaches up to this part, which is
questionable in my mind, but let's say it does,
The topography and the
width of the corridor,
the quality of the corridors is much more
it's it's better suited for for wildlife in general, also for wood turtle.
Whereas the other one in the East is not because of the grade and I could not see a turtle going up
and spending ecological
capital, if you will, and energy to do that. There's nothing for it there.
So the idea was,
okay, let's
let's put a a box culvert.
Let's
embed it into the substrate. Let's recreate the the watercourse underneath the intermittent watercourse.
Let's make sure that it passes
at a minimum of a fifty year storm without
creating
a head behind it, which was one of the
things that mister Hanfield had put in his report, which I see he's also in in this meeting.
It also complies with
Army Corps of Engineers guidelines that we will have to deal with later.
So that was the the major,
if you will, in
my mind. Let's do this. This will be better overall,
allowing for this connectivity to continue without
restriction,
especially for the Western Corridor, which is in my mind the most ecologically significant.
In the meantime, one of the other things that I had heard from the commission,
actually from my client and also from the minutes,
was the question about mitigation.
And that was part of my report that you see there.
Typically,
so we have 2,000 some square feet of disturbance,
at least with the previous plan, and it's probably very similar with the box culvert.
And typically in many, many towns, including your own,
we look for opportunities for in kind mitigation,
which means
specifically
restoration and enhancement and then creation
if
that
opportunity exists. But usually
the creation and the restoration components
blend together because we don't want to take
something
that's already has an ecological value, whether it's upland or wetland,
and take trees down to create a wetland just to create a wetland. So we always look for opportunities
to restore first. If you have a degraded wetland, we go after that.
If there's a wetland that's
not functioning particularly well, we can enhance it, we do that.
And then creation is sort of the last thing that we do in that hierarchy
after, of course, after
the avoidance part. And the avoidance part is have we minimized the
direct impacts to the extent possible?
That's the feasible prudent alternative test.
Having
said that, I did not see any opportunities for wetland restoration
per se,
or for
creation on the site.
But I did see some opportunities for wetland enhancement,
which it's
part of the restoration as opposed to depends on how bad it is.
So what I said in my report that you can see there
is that
as you follow that intermittent stream with a smaller watershed
up the grade where the grade becomes
a little more gentler,
you
leave this very narrow stream border, which has no wetland, no fringe wetlands.
And this wetland opens up to a more gentler slope.
And you've seen it that delineated on the site and actually extends more off the site, you can't see that. But it's
a significant wetland, it's possibly
a little south of an acre altogether if you string everything together.
That unfortunately
is infected with Japanese barberry.
And so my thought was, okay, here's an opportunity,
especially
next to the intermittent stream,
to take a section of intermittent stream from the point where it flattens up coming up the corridor, which is where the
where the barberries
increase
and follow for about a 150 linear feet, go about 15 feet on each side,
and remove
all of the barberry,
which if you look at the understory there, and I wish I'd create a picture,
I would say it's 75% of what's there. So it's an infestation.
And it points back to
the agricultural pastoral
use of this wetland probably several decades ago, probably in the fifties.
So
the idea is to remove it mechanically.
No pesticides,
no herbicides
involved for this one species.
It's very effectively
removed by yanking it.
When
the ground is moist, you can use a weed wrench or you can just
snip and take it off, remove all that mass.
So that's year one.
And then year two,
you come back and you just remove the seedlings.
In my experience,
it very rarely comes back once you remove it mechanically.
And so the only thing you have to deal with is
a few seedlings which you yank on year two. And then the second part of the mitigation
plan that I was suggesting
is to,
know, in the spaces that are creating after a year, not immediately, because you want to see if anything good comes up, and you also removing the seedlings,
is to look
at those vacated places of the understory
and put in a minimum of 50 shrubs. And the 50 shrubs would be the smaller size, so the
number two pot, I guess it's a gallon.
And they're usually
two to three feet,
maybe four
tall. The reason for that is because it is kind of rocky terrain up there. So you basically
gonna have to find a small
nook and cranny to put this shrub in.
And
so I selected a few species there that I thought based on the fact that this is a shaded area would do well.
A spicebush would do well. Winterberry would do fairly well.
Gray dogwood, of course, always does well,
and nannyberry.
The first two species are the wetter spectrum and the second two species are the slightly drier facultative.
So we would have to
select the appropriate areas for that.
But there's a lot of microtopography already. You can choose a slightly higher area versus one that's a little lower.
So that's kind of
in a nutshell
what I have come about. And of course, my conclusion is there in the end of the report
tells you that I believe that
this is the feasible and prudent alternative,
especially something that would likely satisfy the use of Army Corps of Engineers. Although I know, I understand this is not your immediate
concern,
it's our concern.
And then of course, the mitigation there, I believe that the functions and values
of this wetland for the crossing and its ecological continuity
and integrity will continue.
So that's what I have to offer and I'd be happy to answer questions. But before I do that, let me tell you that
I have a double meeting in Madison that I need to get to as soon as possible. So
you may ask me any questions and then I'll, unfortunately, I'll have to leave.
>> Okay.
Thank you,
Mr. Logan.
I will,
begin
coming back asking the commissioners if they have any specific questions or comments
on Mr. Logan's report.
>> Bill Monroe, I have one question about the size of that box culvert.
>> Yeah, I think Mr. Bushnell will be probably a better candidate for answering that question.
>> Oh, okay. So let's
hold that. I was going to ask Mr. Bushnell to comment in just a moment,
but deferring to Mr. Logan's need to get to the other meeting, wanted to specifically
look at
his comments and recommendations.
Was speaking for myself, was happy to see the recommendation
to
eradicate barberry
and to replace it with native shrubs, and I think these are good choices
that should be successful,
as
Mr. Leung pointed out, in specific niches
according to the kind of micro
habitat preferences
for the individuals.
But
I think that
if you look at it with a ten to fifteen year picture in mind,
driving across that bridge flanked by good
cops of
well especially spiced bush in the spring will be a real treat for the owners.
>> This is Jed, and I did have one question.
And
I don't know
the critter type necessarily that we were looking for when you're studying the reptilian
waterways and all that.
But being that this has taken place in February,
would we expect to be able to draw the proper conclusions
on that this time of year?
>> No,
point is well taken. So the idea was to see,
so you can look at the Macrobenzas,
you can see what uses the stream
during this time of the year, and that gives you
a better understanding
of what
the ecology is.
Now, I know,
generally speaking, the kind of critters that
will utilize
this corridor, the small one and the large one.
And so
I don't see
the
with box cover, that shouldn't be any problem for just about any species of small bodied or even medium bodied
species, whether they're forbearers or
herptiles to
come through, others will just climb over and head out.
Of course, they're not going to go through a
eight foot by three foot opening, which I think is what we're going for.
The other side,
again,
my understanding is that what we're doing there is we're keeping the 36 inches pipe,
which is going to pass the fifty year storm,
and we're embedding it slightly
so that there's more of a natural
stream bed, if you will. But that, again, my assessment is that something that we're gonna have to work out with the core.
But in my mind, for
this purpose for now, from a hydraulic perspective, that it is sufficient from what I'm told. And I think for small bodied
animals and also for the Macrobenthes that I saw, that shouldn't be a problem.
So for instance, if this was
a fishery kind of habitat,
a perennial stream, I'd say this is completely unreasonable. You'd have to go with a box culvert
with the openness ratios and so on that the core guidelines specify.
But
this is not the case here. This is a minimal stream with a small watershed,
and its ecological connectivity will be preserved
by the 36 inch pipe.
George, this is Hank.
>> Can I speak? Absolutely. Was going to invite you to speak as a matter of fact, thank thank you.
>> I think George is correct from the ecological connectivity standpoint. And in think my view, you know, that's not really the issue here. And that's not the issue that I really focused
on are primarily raised in my in, you know, when I took a look at the assess the property and submitted a letter.
It is, you know, You
know, it's, you know, wood turtles may use come up to that area where the confluence is but that's not really an issue. And I, and I think the stream biota is George mentioned is not really the issue. To
me, the real challenge here is that it's it's much more of a complex system than just a
Single channel, it's you have a, you know, you have a hydrologic system there that's coming off that that those uplands that is part of a larger riparian corridor that includes the Hop River, which is just downstream from that. Also joined by another another stream coming in just south of the crossing there. So
the concerns that I've raised that I still maintain
problematical
are the physical alterations that will occur. Doctor. In the area where it, you know, you the crossing is in where it's a very wide it's it's almost like a wetland at that point. It's a larger land. If you look at the soils between that, I mean it's pretty mucky, it's a there's a lot of subsurface
flow there, I would suspect. And
my concern is the physical alterations and the potential change to the hydrology
and potential impacts
that will then carry on to the downstream systems, including the Hop River. It's more about the physical characteristics and the hydrological characteristics of that site.
Now you can look at it for as being able to support a fifty year storm event from a drainage and that's great. But remember, we're in fairly changing times and we're seeing extremes
and you know you're going to get you're going to get flashiness in there. It's
clearly a you know it's a well defined
fairly wide system there.
I'm less concerned about the ecology of the, the animals that are using it as habitat because as George mentioned, I believe that's minimal. You
know, there's certainly a part of it, but I think it's more to do with the impacts to that wetland system those those that corridor
and its connection to the Hop River. I'll,
I'll say one other thing. George mentioned Sparrow feasible and prudent alternative.
You know, when looking at this, you know, one feasible in my view anyway feasible and prudent alternative to this is
not to do any crossings at all off of here, but to look at a common driveway that comes off of the entrance off of
old farms that because you could avoid any
of the upland review areas associated
with
though the wetland systems. Now, normally, I don't recommend lengthier
cuts in through forested habitat with driveways. But
as I recall, this one might have been a gravel driveway. But in lieu of, you know, the considerations of the potential of the wetland crossings that are required and the complexity of it. Mean, I think this would be a little different if it was
a single stream court or you know that we had fairly. Doctor.
Distinct upland edges and it wasn't opening up into a confluence there, it'd an easier. Brian
Plan for a cup for a for a crossing.
So,
you know, I guess I would say that, you know, there may be another fee.
Prudent and feasible alternative
that avoids crossing
altogether.
I don't know all I profess that I don't know all the ramifications of that, but I do believe that our our planning and zoning regulations allow for common
driveways.
So that may be one thing to think about.
>> Okay, thank you, Mr. Greer. I'm going to turn this over to
the applicant,
III George Correa,
and Engineer Bushnell.
I think that there were
the alternative
of a driveway,
a shared driveway,
as I believe already been
ruled out. I'm asking the applicant to comment on that and engineer Bushnell as far as the engineering
aspects
of the
revisions
and modifications
and their impact
on the stream and the wetland hydrology.
>> If I may, because again, I apologize,
but I have to leave momentarily.
But I just want to leave you with a few thoughts.
I'm glad to hear that Hank recognizes
the ecological integrity
where it fits in the spectrum of things here. I understand and I agree that it you know, any stream that's
this connectivity with another stream, there's you know, it's a complex system.
And I agree that it's the physical stuff that we need to look at because at the end of the day,
it's the physical impacts that the commission
regulates.
You don't regulate the ecology per se, you do indirectly.
But when it comes to hydrology
and when it comes to hydraulics
and
whether this stream can be passing during fifty or one hundred year storm and all that kind of stuff,
I will defer to Mr. Bushnell who has the qualifications.
Certainly, don't. I can have opinions as soil scientists, obviously. The other thing I want to leave you with, and I think
Mr. Vice Chair, you did talk about the fact that I believe that you can't have another driveway
from
the top,
is when you look at feasible and prudent alternatives,
very often we just focus on the feasible part and we ignore the prudent.
The prudent
also brings into play
the social economic benefit. Economics are part of it, as long as they're not the only part of it.
It's a balancing act.
Something is feasible from an engineering perspective, but something might not be prudent
because it's so economically
unreasonable
that it just basically undermines the objective of the project. But that's something enough for me to make a decision, that's something for the commission to make a decision.
Unless you have another question of me, I will have to depart for the evening.
>> Last opportunity.
Again, you're free to leave and thanks for your participation. Thank you so much. Have a pleasant evening, everyone.
Thank you. Bye bye.
>> So this is Eric Lateska, the co applicant here. I'll just, you
know, maybe give a little bit of the history on that. The
alternative on the other side there,
the access to that, to the property right now
is through a two way,
easement,
through somebody else's property,
to just, just to give access, driveway access,
from Old Farms Road.
This, because what would follow here is a,
a subdivision application,
going from the other side would then require a three way easement, which
is a variance from planning and zoning regulations, but more importantly,
it's something we approach the owners of the property on the other side with,
and we're not able to get them to agree to.
So
it is not an option for us,
unfortunately.
Okay, thank you. Thank you for clarifying.
>> Mr. Bushnell,
your comments on the
hydrology and engineering aspects that were just
raised.
>> As far as the hydraulics
of it, you know, ran some new calcs using the
three by eight
box culvert buried 25%
on
the west side and maintaining the 36 inches
culvert pipe on the east side, again,
buried to
25%.
And we can pass the fifty year storm just with the Box Culvert on its own.
We'll pass the
storm from both watersheds, the fifty year storm with no pressure
in the Box Culvert.
So,
neither the Box Culvert or 36
would
have any pressure in them in a fifty year storm.
Likely what would happen there in fifty year storm,
you're getting a lot quite a bit of flow since the Box Culvert would be a little bit lower elevation than the 36 Inches Culvert. A lot
of the water would go through the Box Culvert
in
that situation.
36 would still take water, but
some of it would start to flow towards the Box Culvert there
because it is pretty flat down in there, was mentioned.
>> Based on the photographs,
it seemed to me that
there
would be very little
visible alteration
of that
depositional area
below or downstream
of the proposed crossing where it seems to go into sort of it's like a delta almost with the
channels crisscrossing.
Yeah,
think you're correct.
>> Any other questions regarding the
permit? Oh, I did ask one question.
Have these proposed changes been reflected on an updated plan
for our files?
>> Not as of yet. Mean, we just came to this late last week and we're
waiting to hear your feedback tonight and then we'll go from there. Okay.
So any other questions or
comments from commissioners?
>> Is this where we should talk about potential
public hearing?
>> This
would be as good as time as any to
bring that up, yes.
So
do you have a proposal?
>> I would make a motion that we hold a public hearing
on this application.
Okay
and
that motion would require a second.
I'll second it.
>> Okay so we have a motion and a second discussion.
Anybody else want to speak? I would ask
specifically
what additional information
we might expect
to obtain
as a result of
holding a hearing.
>> I would hope
that we
would get the opportunity for other members of the public to come in. I can't remember
if
we as a commission asked Hank Bruner to provide input to us or if he came on
his own volition as a member of the Conservation Commission.
And then we also
had
Scott Persson in attendance
at this meeting.
And the last one is an interested member of the public.
And so as we have the first application since I've been on the commission that's been deemed a significant
activity,
I think
we would be well served to see if there are any other
public inputs
that we should take before we make that decision. And that was my
rationale for providing the motion.
>> Okay.
Any other
comments or considerations?
I will say,
Commissioner Larsen,
agree with you that it's probably desirable
to at least solicit
additional public comment
and
looking
forward to
having
more articulate regulation
regarding holding hearings.
I would also
propose that we set such a hearing
as
a prologue
to the regular meeting
as we did with the
hearing that we held for the application at 129
Hebron Road so that we could essentially
have the hearing
and then proceed
to the meeting where the application
would be considered.
And I would hope also by that time we would have sufficient information
based on the record so far and any such comment as might be received in a hearing we would be able to
vote
and make a decision
on the application.
We are still within our legal bounds,
but with the code extensions,
but nevertheless this process has been going on for some time
and I think we owe it to the applicants
to
resolve that
process and bring it to completion.
Any other comments on the motion to hold a hearing?
Seeing that I'll ask for a roll call vote again
following screen or
William.
>> I couldn't hear you because you went in and out for a second. What was the question.
>> Okay, I'm asking for a vote on the motion
for the public hearing. The motion is to hold a hearing
with regard to this application.
Yeah, I.
>> So it's been moved in second to. Okay,
Commissioner Larson.
I vote I as well.
>> Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
And Vice Chair Elliott also votes aye, so the motion carries four-zero-zero.
As I've suggested in the discussion,
I think we should schedule this hearing
to proceed
our next meeting
at which this application
would be considered.
As far as I know that would be the regular meeting
for I believe March 5
and again
we
couldn't
handle the matter
pardon April
5.
>> April 5 sorry yeah unfortunately
not April 1
So April 5 meeting would be again,
we could proceed that
with the hearing,
and I might also
suggest that in lieu of that we could
truncate any public
comment
on the regular agenda.
So, it's
agreeable to the Commission to have the hearing
prior to our regular meeting on April 5.
>> Can I add something? Is Agent White. Sure, Agent White. I was just looking at the calendar for the town.
It looks like
the next wetlands meeting
is on Tuesday,
April 13.
Oh, was there a conflict
for our? Looks
>> like the three meetings, the three other meetings on the first Monday.
>> Is there any reason we couldn't hold a special meeting?
The
conflict is less of an issue if
it's a Zoom meeting.
>> I think the conflict may have had to do with
that first Monday being the day after Easter.
I
don't know the school schedules or whatever,
but
I remember something about vacations and Easter being a cause for moving that.
>> Jed, I believe you're right it is precisely
because
it is the
Monday following
Easter
that
we
unfortunately,
information has not
gone on to my calendar.
Can we just leave it for now at our next regular meeting?
And
we'll check the date and make sure that it gets properly
assigned
in the minutes, okay?
And of course all the typical
warnings and so forth that have to go out.
We'll have time to accommodate
the hearing timeline.
May
I ask a question?
I'm
>> just wondering if we have any
duty here to mail the abutters
for the public hearing? That actually
>> is the obligation
of the Wetlands
agent for his
staff.
Okay.
But that yeah that you paid for that in your application sheet.
>> Okay. Agent Wagner, think we I
we included a list in our application. You have a list of the abutters
>> and yeah, it's a responsibility
under the regulations
for the Commission
or its agent to notify
the abutters of the hearing. It also has to be published, I presume, in the River East
twice
at intervals that are prescribed,
you know, well before and shortly before the actual hearing.
Okay.
So, no, you don't have any requirements as far as the obligation is concerned.
Okay,
>> anything else
regarding this application
okay
then
just wait a minute I gotta pull up the agenda again
So
I guess we can move on now to
item
number
seven
B,
IWWC
2,037
ms for
modification
of a permit that was issued for 344 Lake Road.
I
believe we have
the engineer representing the applicants on the call.
I am on the call. Thank you.
>> And
let's see do we have any
agent Wagner do we have any other
do we have any new information or new
considerations for this application?
No, I haven't received anything.
>> Mr. Hanfield,
did you have any,
comments to bring up anything new to,
relate to the Commission regarding this application?
>> Nothing new there were a couple minor questions in the last
meeting that'll just check off for the record Brandon Hanfield with Yannick River Consultants.
One of the questions with regard
to the
length of the regulated area and I just wanted to point out our plan does reference a 200 foot regulated area and shows
a 200 foot boundary.
I'm not sure where the 100 foot comes from
but I just wanted to point out that our plan does call out a 200 foot regulated area
and our entire property is within that
200 feet.
And then there was also a comment about
moving a utility pole on our property
and yes,
that utility pole will be relocated.
We're not sure how or when
the power company will move it and how they want to move it but in all likelihood it will be moved closer to the street.
It can't be moved closer to the lake.
That's really the only
open questions I had from the last meeting but happy to share the plan again
so people so everyone can see it or answer any questions.
>> Okay yeah that would be helpful Mindy or if you could give Brandon
the desktop
so
we have that plan in front of us. I have it
on my own desktop but I can't share it.
Yep, I just made him a co host.
>> Okay.
I just shared the plan and I'm zoomed in so we're only looking at the
subject building site. I'm happy to zoom out or show other details as need be
But the proposed addition is outlined in bold with the dark gray.
It's about 800 square feet and footprint.
There is a proposed deck
on the lakeside
of the new addition and what you see in a dashed line around that
that goes all the way and attaches to the garage is the addition that was approved
in 2018
by a different applicant. So you see that the proposed building is generally within that original footprint
and any changes to that footprint are on the driveway side not the lake side
of the addition.
Okay.
Again, any questions
from commissioners
regarding the application?
>> Is the soil stockpile
that's indicated on
the drawing
pertinent to the septic repair or is that to the job that's coming up?
>> It's
the job coming up. What I tried to do is take
a realistic approach. So the leaching field's in, there will be no changes to the leaching field or the septic tank. They are code compliant.
So I picked a location where
they can't stockpile on top of that leaching field and we're kind of boxed in by the garage.
So this location here,
they've already take they took these two trees out actually these four trees out as part of the leaching field repair. So it's open and it's easily contained within
silt fence there. So that's the location I chose.
It might not be that big but
I thought it was a reasonable location rather than on the other side of the leaching field closer to the lake.
Thank you.
>> Okay,
any other questions?
Okay, seeing none, I think we're now at a point where we can consider
a motion to approve
this
application.
We've
received it, we've discussed it
and
the statutory
time limit has
elapsed
so
again I would entertain a motion to
approve
IWWC
twenty-thirty
seven ms.
>> I'll make a motion to approve IWWC
twenty-thirty
seven ms at 344 Lake Road.
Okay
and could I have a second to that?
I'll second it.
>> And I will add that we
have
found that the
activity
is
within the scope of the regulations
and that no feasible or prudent alternative exists
to the proposed activity
so that we have all of our i's dotted and our t's crossed.
Would you
enter your hands or what the duration
of permit usually that's going to be the two or five year permit duration?
>> If
I were to say two and I wanna hedge a little, if I were to say two without the applicant online,
we just come can back to
stick with two. I think construction will take a year
and they will start it within two years is that how it usually goes?
>> Okay because we can easily I think we could as easily approve it for five year period to give you that
leeway. I would feel more comfortable but okay.
>> Anybody else want to weigh in on that question? Adrian Wagner, have you experienced
any
problems with an extended
timeline.
>> I don't see why that would be a problem.
Okay. I feel like given the extra time would be
would be good.
>> Who knows the property might change hands again no unlikely I
hope not okay
so
we have a motion and I believe we had a second right
and any further discussion
okay seeing that I'll go through the roll call
Mr. Monroe
aye
Mr. Larson. Aye.
Mr. Halsey.
Aye.
And Vice Chair Elliot also folks aye. So the motion carries 400
the
permit will be issued with standard conditions with a timeline
and of course there's the fourteen day waiting period etc.
But I guess that bottom line you're good to go. Appreciate it.
Okay,
well moving
on we added
an item eight
the
application
for
essentially maintenance work
at
the Doris Chamberlain
Nature Pond
this was received
last Thursday
Major Wagner was it but it hasn't it was so it's too late to go on the agenda
but
the application is complete and
I believe posted on the website
Ken, I guess I'll
ask our meeting administrator,
Mindy, if you could
find that and bring that up.
Essentially, is an
application
by
well let's see now
okay
so the application is basically by the town.
Chamberlain Pond
or the Doris Chamberlain Nature Pond as you may know it
is
used and
I guess probably used since it was first created
for winter
skating
and
that of course is a use permitted as of right, a recreational use of the watercourse,
but over time
the
trees surrounding
watercourse
have decayed,
branches falling and branches overhanging
and the room for skating is getting awfully
narrow.
So, the application
is to essentially
clean up debris
from the margins
of
the pond
and I suppose probably removing some
material
from the pond per se
where you have branches that are emergent
and therefore,
again, obstacles
to the use for ice skating.
Regent Wagner, do you have any
comments? I know you went on a sidewalk
with that and
most of us are familiar
with the pond.
>> Yeah, I just visited it.
Got an explanation.
And, yeah, they basically I I took the pictures,
the branches that you can see sticking out of the ice,
the lower ones. Basically, lower ones are the ones that were they're planning on removing.
And then the dead ones that are in the water, you can see that one that's frozen in the ice.
And then some of the ones that are overhanging, and they were gonna leave the ones that were taller that you could skate underneath, But, basically,
just clearing enough of the
the dead and hanging ones. Yeah. Like, where it's circled there, the the more horizontal branches and
and brush.
Area looks a little clear over there, but
Their hope was to do it
before the ice melted. I don't know if that's gonna happen because the ice is gonna melt pretty quick, probably pretty soon, but, they were gonna do some of it when it was sliced over and then do the rest once it melted with a with a boat either by boat or by waiting.
>> George, this is Scott Persona. If you need any questions, further questions asked, Jeff
>> told me that I could speak for him. Okay, fine, thank you. I think that from the Commission's point of view the only thing we really need to determine right now
is again getting back to our earlier discussion
whether this is a significant
activity.
My
own opinion is that it would not be,
but I think it would be helpful for the record if we had a motion
to the effect
because again if we have
the motion
to deem it a significant activity,
we vote no on that motion,
then we've answered that question
and we can proceed with the application on that basis. So,
just as a matter of process,
I would ask
for
a motion again a motion to the effect that this is a significant activity
so that we can make that determination.
>> I'll make a motion that it is a significant activity.
>> Okay, thank you, Jed. And a second for that motion. Second.
Allicy.
>> Okay, so we've got the motion and a second.
Discussion?
I already discussed it by saying that I don't think that it is a significant activity. That's really
in a sense
although
a
tiny impact on the watercourse per se,
mostly what we're looking at is
on
the shore
of the watercourse,
and it's really enhancing
the
use of the watercourse
for what I mentioned before is a permitted activity.
Any other comments?
>> I guess I'll just ask the question, are we sure that it is
an activity that requires a permit?
I'm not sure that I would have recognized that had it not come my way.
>> I
checked the regulations,
Jud. And yes, recreational activities of water courses
do not require a permit.
They're permitted as of right.
Now, if they wanted to dredge the
watercourse
to enhance its
value that might be another thing but as I say right now we're looking at a permitted use and
simply
maintenance
around it.
Mr. Hollisey, did you have a comment?
>> That was confused.
I mean, my understanding is Jed had asked if it required a permit
and your response was that it was a use of right.
>> The
recreational use, the ice skating. All right. Yes. I
>> recall that Commissioner Wagner bring addressing this in a previous application
that
recreational uses is use of right but not construction of recreation
that working in that area. Does that sound
familiar Joe.
>> Yeah I was looking for the exact regulation because I looked it up for this one and it's yeah
because recreation would be like the act of ice skating or fishing or something, but trimming trees or cutting
brush or removing anything,
though it's to create an area for recreation that's not actually recreation.
So I was looking for the one.
Yes.
Section 4.3
All the regulations are of activities
in wetlands or water courses involving filling, activating, dredging, clear cutting, clearing, grading, or any other alteration.
Not specifically permitted by the section, which
under section 4.1,
it has provision for a residential home.
Use is incidental to the enjoyment or maintenance of residential property.
So if this was a residential property,
I would say this one wouldn't need a permit, but because it's not a residential property,
it does. It doesn't fall under
section
4.1
d.
>> So it falls under section 4.1. You answered my question, agent Wagner. I know I'm not a lawbreaker now when I go out and trim the bushes.
Thank you.
>> Again,
the question here is the motion
has to do with significance and my remarks were simply
to
underscore what I believe to be the
incidental nature
of the work for which a permit is being requested.
Simple fact that it's that,
you know, they're
not asking for permission to
create
an outdoor recreation area. It's already there.
They're just asking for permission
to do maintenance
and most of that maintenance
is on the perimeter
of
the water course,
not within it.
We will still be considering a permit
for the
maintenance.
>> Agent Wagner isn't there something in the regulations that says maintenance of
existing.
Structures
or
roads.
>> Yeah. There is.
I'm looking for the specific section.
Yeah. There is, but it doesn't it's not
it's like maintenance of drainage pipes.
Let's see.
Yeah. Maintenance relating to any
drainage pipe
on property, which is where you can remove vegetation
to clear like a drainage pipe that was installed prior to
1974.
There's
nothing for for
maintenance of a pond, though.
>> Again, as I say, we're not considering the question here whether or not a permit is required.
It's just the only question that we're addressing right at the moment is whether or not the proposed activity
is a significant activity
under
regulations.
And once again, I would argue that it is not and that we should
vote no on the motion
and thereby deem
that it is not a significant activity.
Any other questions or comments on the motion?
Okay, ask for a
roll call vote. Commissioner Monroe.
No.
Commissioner Larson.
Mr. Halsey.
No.
And Vice Chair Elliott also votes no. So the motion is defeated
40.
And we can now move on with that application.
Again, we'll have to wait until our next regular meeting
to make an actual
determination
on the
application,
but this would certainly be an appropriate time if commissioners have any questions
that they might address to selecting person who
is
speaking for the, I guess, representing the applicant
in this application.
>> I have a question. Sure.
Who would be doing the work? Would this be the Conservation Commission?
>> I think that Jeff Murray and the Conservation Commission were involved with this.
Yeah.
Thank you. I was just curious.
Any other questions,
comments.
>> Anybody want get a great idea the
a lot of good works going on over there at the last year so it's looking much better than it did
and I think.
>> Just trying to look at make it look nice and usable this year they could have used it for
you know a couple months now but.
>> Couldn't skate around there. Do we want to have a bedding pool
or whether or not you'll be able to get on the ice
or what day
the car will fall through the ice is just the betting pool, right? As
the agent Wagner said, it's not looking so good
for being able to
get out of there to do the work
for the near future. We'll be taking a boat.
>> Canoes and kayaks will be the mode of operation.
Okay, well I guess that's really all we can do on that application for now.
So, we'll have the application on our agenda
for our next meeting and hopefully at that time we'll be able to make a determination.
So, then moving on
Oh god, yes, number nine. What's now number nine? Enforcement actions.
We are still looking at the conditions on 33 Route 87
agent Wagner the last time I drove on Route 87 that trailer that that
shed was still where it had been
has there been any change
No, it was a couple of weeks ago. No,
>> spoke with Kurt.
He said Mark
Williams, the contractor,
has been waiting for the weather to warm because the shed is frozen to the ground So I can't move it without damaging it.
It's probably getting pretty close to being able to move now.
Except the ground will be too wet.
Yeah.
>> But yeah, so it's
a nothing's nothing's happened there in the past month.
>> Okay,
well, same old same old.
Commissioner, has anybody got anything to say? Any comments,
questions,
suggestions,
COVID or Dicta?
Okay then
eight or nine b the
situation at 27 Hendee Road.
>> Yeah, I found
looked up the plan for construction,
at the property. There was a
site plan submitted to the town on 05/17/2018.
Shows a silt fence.
So according to the plan, there should be a a geotextile
fabric silt fence, which extend
from the northwest part of the property, south along Hendy Road, and then turn north along
the existing driveway near the house and then it should follow the driveway north. It turns to the east and it turns north again, falls at the tree line at the top of the hill to the west of the Hop River.
And the soap fences aren't currently installed.
So I sent a
certified letter to Mr. Rivera asking him to install the soap fence when the weather permits.
So
that's where I'm at with that. Okay,
>> was there any observation of erosion or siltation
on the site?
>> I couldn't see any when I looked there. I mean you could see some through the trees I don't know if the construction was caught was causing it and then and then of course there was a lot of snow cover up until
right week or so.
>> Okay
still in all if there's a permanent requirement we should require it. Yeah.
Okay, any other questions
or comments
regarding the
enforcement
actions?
Okay, that would segue then into what's now on-ten.
Agent Wagner, do you have any other items to report? I believe there were some
upland review permits issued something like that. Yeah, there was two
>> upland review permits.
There was one for the Hillside Self Storage Center on 132
Route 6.
They're
reinforcing the existing timber retaining wall,
replacing
400 cubic yards of stone riprap
in the upland review area between the existing timber retaining wall and the delineated wetlands.
I met the engineer Andrew Bushnell on the site February 5.
He explained the project they're gonna
use the excavator to place the riprap
from above. So they're gonna go from the the storage area up above and drop the riprap down just to
shore up the wall because it's it's timber and it's all starting to deteriorate and collapse.
And they're gonna place it to the edge of the wetlands, which were delineated
and they're all flagged.
And then I was contacted by the property owner earlier today, and he said they're probably going to start work as early as this Thursday, but probably
Monday March 8
is the likely date for that to start.
And then
there was a second agent approval on 33 Gilead Road, which is a
removing an eight foot by eight foot shed that's at the end of a gravel driveway and replacing it with a
12 by 24 foot prefabricated
garage,
which will be sitting on a 14 by 26 stone pad and it's going to be placed
in the area of the old shed and onto the existing
gravel driveway.
And that's all an upland review and it's all
lawn around it
so it's pretty minimal impact
so yeah those were the two for this month
>> Okay,
any questions from the Commission
on those actions?
Okay,
hearing none then we can move on now to agenda item number 10 number 11
our other business category
and again
per
the
previous
modifications
we dropped the discussion of the nature pond brush clearing
and
substituted
then well
then
that
leaves
Former B as the next item, the possible action
on the revised
bylaws.
Last meeting
and
prior to last meeting,
had
well, Agent Wagner and myself
gone through
the
previous edition of our
bylaws
to make
such changes
as might be
advisable or required.
Agent Wagner
made considerable revision on some of the language
and I made a couple of additions regarding
conduct
of meetings and hearings,
especially when they're held here are now
on a virtual platform.
We
left off a discussion
of the proposed
revisions to the bylaws,
noting that we would have to wait until this meeting
before any action could be taken
to approve
the revisions.
Again, that's a requirement.
So, at this point,
I would like to
entertain a motion
to approve the
of the bylaws and then we can go on and discuss
that
motion.
So, motion again a motion to approve the revisions to the bylaws.
This would be the document
so we're all on the same page
it was
bylaws revision 2021
gs
was the last version that was distributed.
Make a motion to approve the updated bylaws.
>> Okay,
motion. Could I have a second? Second.
Okay, so we have a motion by Larsen and a second by Halsey to approve
the revised
bylaws.
So now we can open that
to discussion. Again, a brief summary I gave you
and I would
hope to hear from commissioners who have gone through it with a fine tooth comb
and found the typos and misstatements
that almost invariably
get through any such process.
>> I have two
items I'd like to bring up.
Okay. One is item four-three.
It talks about,
if it's four-three, talks about filling vacancies.
Just a second, I'm trying to open that document.
>> Bylaws themselves are rather confusing to me.
And I went to the charter
and the charter was a little confusing as well. I think what I'd like to point out is
we're talking about
filling vacancies
that arise.
And the charter
speaks about filling vacancies
initially or July 1,
which are so those are filled by the
the Board of Selectmen.
But if you look in what's proposed,
it would seem that we're sending,
it's very unclear what happens to me, at least it was very unclear to me what they were trying to say.
I believe the
intent is
that the commission itself
fill the vacancies
that arise
outside of an election period of
the cycle, the election cycle.
That's correct.
>> It's that
way the proposed,
I believe it's section four-three.
Hopefully I'm referencing
the right
section.
>> Okay, the revised section 4.3
prescribes the process of notification
for
vacation notification of vacancies arising from a resignation
or other cause
And then the process,
which
the
acceptance,
the initial appointment
is made
in this situation,
the appointment to fill
would be made by the
Commission membership. Now, remember that would only be good for the remainder
of the term
and reappointment
and in fact that would be communicated
to the Board of Selectmen
and
it would be then
the
privilege of the Board of Selectmen
at the
reappointment
the
seat.
And of course it also provides that if we don't do it, the Board of Selection
has to take care of it.
>> Okay, you know, it's clear to me now.
It just, it hasn't been handled that way in the past. It's
kind of led some confusion.
Okay, thank you. You're welcome. One other minor issue is
you look at section 6.3 and it's I believe
responsibilities
are off
duties of staff.
I
believe this is just a typo for
the weapons officers.
Look under
the last one appear at court proceedings by order of the court at the direction of town council or the commission.
I don't know whether,
I don't know what they mean by town council,
whether it's meant to be board of selectmen or town council spelled
differently
as in town attorney.
It's one of the other though.
To the board of selectmen or town council.
>> Good
point. Good point. Share a note.
It would
wonder where that boilerplate came from.
>> I would guess it would be the Board of Selective.
Although I well
I would guess that's
referring to
>> that would certainly be the only other reasonable
agency
that
could direct
the wetlands enforcement officer.
>> Well I mean really it should be the
town administrator.
I mean staff doesn't staff works for the town administrator.
>> That becomes right so that yeah the the direction
would come from the Board of Selectmen
to the town administrator
right or
from
the inland wetlands commission
okay so shoot so
essentially we should
revise that from town council
to
town administrator?
I think so yeah I think that's more appropriate.
>> Okay.
Okay I got that.
Any other
comments,
questions?
Okay,
right now
the document
still has a bunch of markup in it and you
know everything's highlighted in different colors and so forth and so on but what
I would do is assuming
we vote
affirmatively
I will complete the revision including the language we just discussed
and I will date
the revisions
today 03/01/2021.
I can send that I guess I should send that to you Agent Wagner to
get into
a finalized one on a PDF
that can be then posted
on our website
to replace the current
version of regular bylaws
that are posted
on our page.
I mean, there's
an
administrative
approval or procedure for getting stuff onto the website right yeah once it's once
>> it's finalized by the Commission then I can yeah
I can
put it in
>> Okay, so basically, I'll give you the penultimate version,
and
you can take it from there as far as getting it posted.
And, of course, distribute it to the to the Commission.
Okay,
so we've got a clear idea of what we're going to do there.
So, getting back to the motion, we have the motion and a second to approve the revised bylaws
and
I'll
give one last chance for questions or comments
and then I'll go ahead and ask for a vote. Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson?
Commissioner Halsey?
Aye.
>> And Vice
Chair Elliott also votes aye so the motion to approve the revised bylaws
carries four-zero-zero.
Okay moving on.
Going back to the agenda
which is now buried three deep in other documents
okay
oh that was upland review permit approvals
I think that may have already been handled or was there some other additional
question or comment there
agent Wagner just
>> I don't think so, I think that was already approved,
that was something that
>> Okay, so I was just a carry over. Yeah, I think
it was it was kind of a duplicate.
>> Okay,
then
the
final item under
other business
would be the item added to the agenda,
well two items added to the agenda. First, let's take the
matter of the resignation of the chair.
We have the letter that was distributed
by Megan Lolly
resigning
effective immediately
in a letter dated today.
I guess that it would be
prudent of us to accept that regulation
and then discuss
how we should move forward from there. So
I'd like first a motion to accept the resignation.
>> I'd like to move to accept the resignation of Megan Lally as Chairman of the Inland Islands Commission with regret.
Yes.
Second.
I'll second.
>> Okay. So a motion
by Halsey,
second by Larson
to accept with regret the resignation
of Megan Lowell as Chairman
of the
Innerlecans and Water Courses Commission.
The vote on that motion
would be in order. Commissioner Monroe.
Aye.
Commissioner Larson.
Commissioner Hallisey.
Aye.
>> And
Vice
Chair Elliott also votes aye.
And again, our appreciation
to
Ms. Lalie for the service
that she has rendered.
Moving forward,
I will, as Vice Chair,
am willing to continue
pro tem as
Chair.
I hope, although I have not consulted yet with
Ms. Lawley, that she will assist me as a sort of Vice Chair. There may be times when I won't be able to serve and
we certainly need to have some provision
for a designated
alternate
to
run the meetings
if I can't. But as I say, I'm perfectly willing
to take the helm as vice chair and simply I will ask Megan first
and then
if any of you
want to get a little administrative
experience on this Commission,
I would welcome
your
input
and participation.
>> Would it be appropriate
to
not to make a nomination at this point?
>> You know, it's not covered in the bylaws.
I couldn't find anything in the bylaws about resignation. We have, of course, provision for resignation of members, but
Ms. Lawley
expressed a desire to continue
on the commission but as a regular member and the only provision of the bylaws
is for an election
at
the regular time at the end of the year at the end of the fiscal year.
So, what I would
suggest right now,
Christian Halsey, is that we hold off until the next meeting
as I say I would like to sound out
Ms. Lolly
as to whether she would be willing to kind of swap roles
pro
form a and then we can discuss a kind of an interim appointment
to make it official
or feeling that we can grasp at straws.
Okay
earlier in the meeting
we were talking about legal
guidance,
I mentioned that
some
points of contention
arose with respect to interpreting
the regulations
and
the
let's see I got to find the document but in
the communications
with Attorney Brantz
there was
he acknowledged the fact that okay here I have I found it again
he acknowledged that the
language of that of
regulation
9.1
about public meetings
public hearings excuse me is
vague or it's confusing
it's
simply
there's there are some
double negative
implications
in there and I think that that my understanding is this that the regulation we have in our regulations
is
boilerplate
from
DEEP
suggestions
that have
some history
and
this is an area where we might want to address
a little bit of revision to make that regulation actually say what we want it to say.
The
question, as Humpty Dumpty said, is who's to be mastered?
So, let's get that regulation fixed up. Now, we've been holding fire on regulations.
We talked to it's
been over a year, I think, since we dealt with revising
the regulations and adopting
all of the updates to the regulations
that were necessitated
by changes in
Connecticut state statutes.
And we have, I think,
revised regulations
that are pretty near
ready to go
but
we do need to finish I think the revisions that I just mentioned
and
we need to have a hearing.
Once again I think we could have a hearing
simply
to proceed
the regular meeting
since
frankly I wouldn't expect a huge
amount of public comment
on the regulations
since the revisions reflect only
statutory
requirements
and
clarification.
We're not introducing anything
new
on our own
so I can't see a whole lot of public comment coming out. So, think it's the sort of thing we could handle with a brief hearing
prior to the meeting
which we can then
discuss
adopting
the revised regulations.
It's something we really need to take care of.
So, any comments,
Any suggestions Is as to where we
>> there a copy of the updated regs online?
It's been a while since I
recall us talking about that. And I certainly haven't looked at anything new so I wouldn't be prepared to discuss it
tonight but if it's out there to review I will.
>> Jed, I don't believe that those have been posted. What's posted online is our
current regulations
right dating back to
whenever they were last
modified but I will I have in my files
a copy of the
workup
you know the document we were working on for revisions
and I could certainly distribute that
well in advance. I won't say I'll do it tomorrow but I can certainly
guarantee
to
distribute it well in advance of any
meeting or
here. It would have to be posted prior to the hearing
and of course the hearing has to be appropriately
warned.
We can't
I mean my
feeling is probably the May
regular meeting would be the first occasion
when we might be able to
hold a hearing and
discuss it and, you know, discuss adoption. Now, if I get the
revisions out sooner,
we could certainly have it as a topic for discussion on the other business
at our April meeting.
So we might want to shoot for at least having a
quick look see
at the provost, you know, kind of sort of get back up to speed
on the revisions
at our next regular meeting and then the following regular
regular meeting
could
accommodate
a
public hearing
component
>> Yeah.
Commissioner
Elliot.
Yeah. I am assuming that there would actually be an application
involved
required
coming
from the wetlands commission.
And I also, I don't know what the
comment period might be,
who the
revisions would be distributed to for comments such as
Capital Region Council or Governments, whoever, I don't know,
and what that turnaround is so just just throwing it out there because sometimes it's all right good point I will I will certainly want I'll
>> definitely look into that I don't recall
anything in the regulations
about modified but off the top of my head I don't recall
anything specific about that but I will certainly look.
Okay
>> thanks. Yeah it's probably not there George because
we had the same issue come up with the lake regulations.
And
I was
surprised,
just like you are, when Jim brought that item up. And there are requirements to go out and
get them looked at by other folks.
I don't know where you'd expect to find that but
Jim knew about it. Okay. I was thankful for that. Well,
>> now that I know look for there's at least a known unknown as opposed to an unknown unknown.
So that's progress.
Okay, anything else on that subject?
I
did
have
the opportunity to look through
Attorney Brantz's
comments,
you know,
very often this is a matter of just, as he says, looking through the right end of the telescope.
I was looking at the regulation point of view of what does it say
and
he's looking at the regulations for what does it want you to do?
And
considering that
what we wanted to do is the important thing
we
want to I think
make sure that the language
says what we wanted to do
rather than trying to strain our interpretation
based on language that's unclear.
Okay
back
to the agenda
and lo and behold I believe that is it
as
we previously discussed our next meeting will actually
be on
April
where's my calendar going
is it
Was it April
Joe.
I think it's the
thirteenth.
>> Okay April 13
so Tuesday 04/13/2021
our next regular meeting.
Yeah.
>> So that will be a regular meeting and remember we need to schedule a hearing
prior to that regular meeting
for the
Times Farm Road application.
Okay and finally last but not least
I will entertain
a motion for adjournment.
So moved.
And a second?
I'll second.
>> Okay, the proposition is non debatable,
so we will act
by clicking on our no,
we'll vote on the motion.
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
Larson?
Policy.
Aye.
Motion to adjourn carries four zero zero. The meeting is adjourned
at 08:53PM.
Thank you all for contributing
to the meeting and I'll look forward to seeing you next time.
Mindy, if you have any questions about things that were said or brought into record, contact me. I have most of the documentation
that might help fill in the blanks
in the recording.
Okay, thank you.
>> Hey George,
nice job on the filets. I know there were a lot of work, thank you. Thank you.
>> It wasn't what I signed up for but
you know
I guess it was.
I thought Vice Chairman okay I can do that but I just said freedom.
I didn't didn't mean to get promoted
okay
but
we'll see what we can get done and again
appreciate your assistance
so
we look forward to seeing you next time and we can now
click on the
leave the meeting button. Good night everybody.
Good night all. Good night.